http://youtu.be/glkEjtsAR6M
khang_vgu
Dr. Ramesh Yerraballi: Professor Valvano, what are we
Dr. Ramesh Yerraballi: giáo sư Valvano,
going to learn today?
ta sẽ học gì hôm nay?
Dr. Jonathan Valvano: Today we will learn about the basic building blocks
Dr. Jonathan Valvano: hôm nay ta sẽ học về các khối hợp nhất cơ bản
of all modern electronics, which is the transistor.
là bóng bán dẫn - transistor
Which can be thought of as a switch.
hoặc có thể xem như công tắc
Dr. Ramesh Yerraballi: So what's the point of learning about transistors?
Dr. Ramesh Yerraballi: vậy ta học gì về bóng bán dẫn?
Dr. Jonathan Valvano: Don't you want to know how everything works?
...
We will learn about the n-channel and the p-channel transistor.
ta sẽ học về bóng bán dẫn n và p
And we will put them together to build some simple logic, like an AND gate or
ta sẽ kết hợp các loại đó lại và tạo các mạch lôgic cơ bản như, cổng AND, NOT
a NOT gate.
...
So we can take these basic building blocks, which are transistors, and
vì vây, ta có thể lấy cái khối hợp nhất cơ bản này, là các bóng bán dẫn, để tạo các cổng
build gates.
...
And these gates can be put together to build higher level logic.
các cổng này có thể kết hớp lại để tạo nên mạch lô-gic cao cấp hơn
Like decoders, multiplexers, adders, and multipliers.
như bộ dịch mã, bộ đa công, bộ cộng và bộ nhân
Dr. Jonathan Valvano: Yes.
vâng
And this is called 'Digital Logic Design'.
đây được gọi là thiết kế lô-gic số
Dr. Ramesh Yerraballi: That sounds like a vast topic in itself.
Dr. Yerraballi: nó là đề tài lớn
Dr. Jonathan Valvano: Yes, it is.
vâng
But we will show you just a few simple things, just to give you a glimpse of
nhưng ta chỉ học về những thứ cơ bản, cho bạn thấy sơ về
how the real computer works.
các máy tính làm việc như thế n